# Miguel Rivera-Lanas

Data scientist/engineer with 4 years experience in investment management. Interested in research roles focusing on ML/AI bias and computational social science. Primarily focused on empirical methods to study quantitative and social effects of disinformation propagation and content moderation systems.

### **EXPERIENCE**

# **Data Scientist / Engineer** — **Point72**, NYC, NY September 2019 - Present

- Sept 2019 to Aug. 2020, I was part of a research and learning group, investigating novel applications of data science to prove use cases for alternative data sets as part of the investment process.
- In Sept. 2020, I joined an 8 person, \$X billion investment team, where I manage all data science and engineering projects.
- Implement statistical descriptive modeling, preprocessing, feature engineering, and forecasting over a diverse range of data sets related to oil well production, retail consumer trends, and other sectors.
- Analyze sector exposure to risk factors, inter sector correlations, and build systematic strategy backtesting framework
- Build scalable and robust cloud based event-driven ETL architecture for delivering continuous reporting of data products

# Research Associate, Fixed Income — AllianceBernstein, NYC, NY June 2016 - August 2016, June 2017 - August 2019

- Rotations as research associate for macro economics, quantitative research, and portfolio strategy technology teams
- Developed and maintained ETL, preprocessing, and reporting for novel liquidity signals from live order-book data, utilized by traders to better assess supply and demand conditions for specific parts of the market.

# **Research Assistant** — Wharton Management Dep., Philadelphia, PA September 2015 - May 2016

 Compiled original research on Canadian and Brazilian oil drilling infrastructure projects as part of a long term study focusing on project management best-practices. Used LexisNexis for primary source research on effects of macroeconomic trends and operational decisions.

# **EDUCATION**

**University of Pennsylvania,** Philadelphia, PA — *B.A., Cum Laude* **August 2013 - May 2017** 

Major: Economics, Minors(s): Statistics, International Relations

## Clubs:

- Check One: Board Member. Student organization providing a space for discussions about personal and societal experiences about race and mixed-heritage backgrounds.
- **Penn Journal of Economics:** *Editorial Committee.* (PJE) is a semi-annual, peer-reviewed publication of honors theses and other academic projects for undergraduates and faculty.

Email: rivera.lanasm@gmail.com

**Github:** rivera-lanasm **Website:** rivera-lanasm.com

### **CORE COMPETENCIES**

**Scripting:** Python, Scala, R

**Development:** Git, Airflow, Docker **Cloud:** AWS (S3, EC2, RDS, Lambda,

SNS, Glue Jobs)

**Databases:** PostgresSQL, MongoDB **ML:** Sklearn, Tensorflow, SpaCy **Data Manipulation:** Pandas, Numpy, SciPy, BeautifulSoup, Spark, Tidyverse

Web Dashboard: Plotly Dash

### **INTERESTS**

Computational Social Science, Misinformation, Fairness/Bias in ML/AI

### PERSONAL PROJECTS

Visit www.rivera-lanasm.com/post/

- Logic/Probability Puzzles:
- Logic and math puzzles solved with analytical and probabilistic methods. Solutions coded primarily in **Scala**.

### **VOLUNTEERING**

- Statisticians without Borders
- Consulted NGO over 10 weeks as part of a volunteer team
- Implemented data pipelines and a web dashboard tracking epidemiological model results related to COVID-19 spread in various cities in India.

### **LANGUAGES**

English (Fluent), Spanish (Fluent), French (Working Proficiency)